<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iosuahs godly resolution in conference with Caleb, touching houshold gouernement for well ordering a familie With a twofold catechisme for instruction of youth; the first short, for the weaker sort, set forth in sixe principall points; the latter large for other of greater growth, and followeth the order of the common authorized catechisme, and is an explanation thereof: both set forth for the benefit of his Christian friends and wel-willers. by Richard Bernard preacher of Gods word, at Woorksoppe in Nottingam-shire.</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848546</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13647</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13647)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iosuahs godly resolution in conference with Caleb, touching houshold gouernement for well ordering a familie With a twofold catechisme for instruction of youth; the first short, for the weaker sort, set forth in sixe principall points; the latter large for other of greater growth, and followeth the order of the common authorized catechisme, and is an explanation thereof: both set forth for the benefit of his Christian friends and wel-willers. by Richard Bernard preacher of Gods word, at Woorksoppe in Nottingam-shire.</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641. Large catechisme.</author>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641. Double catechisme.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Legatt, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne by Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts (register is continuous). Part 2 reprints Bernard's "A double catechisme, one more large, following the order of the common authorized catechisme, now this second time published: the other shorter" (STC 1936), a revised version of his "A large catechisme" (STC 1955.5) with the short catechism.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 caption title reads: The catechisme.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13647:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13647:1"/>
            <p>IOSVAHS GODLY Reſolution in conference with Caleb, touching houſhold gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for well ordering a familie.</p>
            <p>WITH A twofold Catechiſme for inſtruction of youth; the firſt ſhort, for the weaker ſort, ſet forth in ſixe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall points; the latter large for other of greater growth, and followeth the order of the common Authorized Catechiſme, and is an explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof: both ſet forth for the benefit of his Chriſtian friends and wel-willers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD BERNARD</hi> preacher of Gods word, at Woorksoppe in Nottingam-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Pet. 2. 2.</bibl> As new-borne babes deſire that ſincere milke of the word, that ye may grow thereby.</q>
            <p>Printed at London by IOHN LEGATT, Printer to the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge, and are to be ſold in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne by Simon Waterſon. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13647:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13647:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir Henrie Pakenham Knight, and to his religiouſly affected Ladie, all good and ſound comforts ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the beſt and moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ioyes in glorie are heartily wiſhed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worſhipfull: man was made for his Creators glorie; the way is to know him, to obſerue his good pleaſure, and with alacrity of ſpirit to doe his will; Though all receiue <hi>Being</hi> of him, yet moſt, as the Heathen, know him not at all. Some ſort in the world profeſſe him: but are little obſeruatiue of his will: theſe onely ſay, Lord, Lord; and therewith reſt ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: other doe aske, what he would haue done; and when they know his pleaſure, they haue it onely vpon their tongue, but far from practiſe. Very few know with faith, and doe what they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and know, with conſcience. Turks for their liues, are as good as many Chriſtians: and theſe
<pb facs="tcp:13647:3"/> no better then other, but for an idle profeſſion. Meanes ſure haue we many to amend this; as his holy word, his multitude of mercies and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold chaſtiſements: But the firſt is deſpiſed, therefore it preuaileth not: the ſecond is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefully abuſed, and mercies mooue vs not: and the laſt is contemned, we grow hard, and therefore o Lord ſaue vs, for iudgements re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime vs not. But the godly wiſe, will I hope, lay theſe things to heart, though moſt be careleſſe: leſt correction turne to deſtruction, mercies be remooued, and of the Goſpel we be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued. The Lord may thus doe, it is our deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing; that by iuſtice he reuenge not himſelfe of vs, it is mercy ſtill without any mans merit God make vs thankefull, that our knowledge may cauſe an acknowledgment heartily, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment ſeriouſly, ſo ſhall we enioy what we haue, and haue what yet we poſſeſſe not, for our greater good.</p>
            <p>My words of complaint and my heartie wiſh tend to ſtirre vp ſome to well doing, that, if ſo. God pleaſe, in a world of wickedneſſe, there may be found <hi>Noahs</hi> preparing the Arke, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Lots</hi> dwelling in <hi>Sodome,</hi> that when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction commeth, ſuch may find in that day fauour in Gods ſight for themſelues and their families. For this end I haue ſent forth, with the principles of religion, and the points of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:13647:3"/> certaine inſtructions deliuered Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue wiſe, teaching and perſwading all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to a mutuall care of one an others ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; euery houſhold gouernour, with the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, to an orderly diſpoſing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that Ieſus Chriſt may dwell amongſt them, and that the houſes of Chriſtians may be lodgings for the Lord, and not dennes of infidells, or habitations of diuells.</p>
            <p>What hath bin deliuered after an other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the ſame changed for a more eaſie informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I now offer (right Worſhipfull) thankefully vnto you: let it pleaſe you to accept my litle la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for your Worſhips ſo large kindneſſe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhewed. I do acknowledge my ſelfe beholden: I profeſſe readineſſe, to expreſſe ſtill more thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, as time ſhall afforde fit occaſion. In the meane ſpace I ſhall not ceaſe to pray for you, that <hi>Ioſuahs</hi> reſolution may be euer in you, that you may follow the ſteppes of Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> and your good Ladie imitate the holy graces of <hi>Sarah,</hi> to your houſholds happineſſe, and both your endleſſe comforts here and in heauen,</p>
            <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Workſoppe, <date>Auguſt. 1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be commanded, <hi>Richard Bernard.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13647:4"/>
            <head>Ioſuahs reſolution of houſhold gouernment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ioſua. 24. 15.</bibl>
                  <p>But I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <stage>IOSVA, CALEB.</stage>
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET me ſpeake vnto you<note place="margin">Coherence of the text with that which went before.</note> (O yee houſe of Iſrael) our fathers haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mercy diuers wayes, wee their children haue experience of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our God; we haue ſound proofe of his aſſured promiſe, vs hath he deliuered, our enemies confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; hath giuen vs poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as appeareth this day. Now my aduiſe and will is, that you would therefore feare the Lord, &amp; ſerue him in vprightneſſe and truth, and ſerue him alone, abandoning all idolatry, and not follow your own corrupt wayes, nor errors of Forefathers, in ſo great an euill. If it ſeeme good vnto you, ſo to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13647:4"/> doe, I ſhall reioyce, it is that I wiſh heartily for your good: but if you will not, bee it knowen vnto you all this day, and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of my full determination herein, <hi>that I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>God forbid, God forbid, that wee ſhould (O moſt noble Prince) be of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, then ſo alſo with thee, to ſeeke the honour of our God, and to ſerue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Surely you well perſwade mee of Gods continuing mercy to vs hereby, for if we ſeeke him, he will be found of vs, if we<note place="margin">2. Chr. 15. 2 1. Sam. 2.</note> honour him, he will honour vs, but if wee forſake him, he will forſake vs. It is alſo my hearts ioy that we do conioine as one here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: but neuertheles this know, that though company doe encourage men to ſerue the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>Firſt</label> Lord, yet if a man be alone, and all do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, that is no barre that a <hi>reſolued Chriſtian</hi> ſhould deſiſt in his holy purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Godly men tie not their religion <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
                  </label> vpon other mens ſleeues, they reſolue with <hi>Peter</hi> to follow Chriſt, if all els doe forſake him: thy words (<hi>Ioſuah</hi>) declare herein thy iudgement, and thy promiſe, what wee all ought to practiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Therefore, as I purpoſe, ſo ought <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> ye to walke with God alone, if none will elſe ioyne with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13647:5"/>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Vrge, I beſeech thee, this point vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people with reaſons, that they may ſee how they may perſwade themſelues herein to a reſolution.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord in giuing his law doth <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                  </label> ſpeak ſingularly in the ſecond perſon, as to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> one man, <hi>Thou</hi> ſhalt haue no other Gods before me, <hi>Thou</hi> ſhalt make no grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and ſo in the reſt, as if he had ſaid; Though other will not ſerue me, though ſome will haue other Gods, though all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will commit idolatrie, yet ſee <hi>thou</hi> doe not ſo, I charg al as one, &amp; one as al, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man may be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſingle himſelfe forth alone to ſerue me the Lord his God.</p>
               <p>Againe, we all do couenant one by one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> at our baptiſme, and ſome doe promiſe as much for this &amp; that Infant, that in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular God ſhall by them be worſhipped: now God will require the performance of the couenant, which bindeth vs vpon the holy Sacrament, and by that ſigne of the ſprinkling of Chriſts blood vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, that ſo we do ſerue the Lord, albeit other do not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed it is an honeſt mans part to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Simil. </seg>
                  </label> keepe his word with men, as we ſee when two are bound in a bond, one, he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects his credit, will performe the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though the other be careles: how much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13647:5"/> more ought we to regard to keep our word with God, the promiſe being made ſo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, before ſo many witneſſes, and ſealed with the blood of Chriſt? This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were ſufficient to perſwade, but if you haue any more, I beſeech you proceed, for we need much ſpurring to run on the race to eternall life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Our Sauiour tels vs, that we are to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> forſake father and mother,<note place="margin">Luke 14</note> wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yea to hate them for his ſake and the Goſpel, els can we not be his Diſciples: by which he teacheth this inſtruction, that we are to depend on none in our religion to God, be held backe by none, from our wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with God: that all earthly affection muſt be laid aſide, and we muſt embrace Chriſt and the Goſpel alone, if none nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther father nor mother, ſiſter nor brother, will goe with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed men in matters of this life, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> will, for wealth, honor, pleaſure: ſingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from other, they would be in honor alone, they would dwell alone, that the poore cannot tell where to haue reſt for them, they can be ſingular in vanity, be pointed out for a new faſhion, be loathed for beaſtly liues, be hated for oppreſſion, be talked of for pride, be abhorred for vnchaſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13647:6"/> conuerſation, blaſphemy, &amp; prophanenes, and yet men are loath to be any whit more religious towards God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other be. Thus alas, we ſee, men hold it no ſhame to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious in and for the world, in &amp; for their pleaſures, in &amp; for honor; <hi>Sathan</hi> can make them grow more vaine, more wicked, then other, without ſhame, without daunt of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, without feare of man, either to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or pointed at: but the Lord cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs by his word to become more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then other; that is forſooth ſingularity, and men feare now a dayes more to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for any ſtrict courſe of life, from a common road, then for crying ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>This ſheweth the power of <hi>Sathan</hi> in the one, &amp; the litle loue or zeale of God in the other, the wicked herein ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne theſe, though they ſhall not ſo ſaue themſelues: but to proceed; If we conſider that we are made alone, brought out alone, that we die in our appointed time alone, &amp; that though wee ſhall <hi>all</hi> appeare before God in the laſt day, yet muſt <hi>euery one</hi> giue<note place="margin">om. 14. 13. Cor. 5. 10.</note> an account for himſelfe vnto God, we ſhould walke and liue, if ſo we needs muſt with God alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>I know if a man haue a long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">simil. </seg>
                  </label> to goe, &amp; that vpon a hard penalty, he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13647:6"/> would deſire honeſt company, but if he can get none, the feare of puniſhment maketh him ſet forward alone. We all are in our iourney to heauen by our profeſſion, and we muſt be ſo by our practiſe, vpon paine of damnation; if we can get any to goe in a good life with vs, it is well, but if not, muſt we therefore herein ſtay our courſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Be it farre from vs; the example of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> holy men, who are as marks ſet vp for paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to look vpon, ſhew vs the contrary. <hi>Noah</hi> would ſerue God alone, when all the<note place="margin">Gen 6.</note> old world was drowned in wickednes. <hi>Lot</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> was in his ſingular way from al the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,<note place="margin">1. King 19. 2. Chro. 18. Ruth. 1.</note> in the midſt of Sodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Eliah</hi> was alone, <hi>Michaiah</hi> auouched the truth alone: &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, <hi>Ruth</hi> would go alone with <hi>Naomi,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Orpha</hi> her ſiſter left her. We muſt be of <hi>Ruths</hi> mind towards religion, as ſhew was in her loue to <hi>Naomi.</hi> If anything would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw vs, if any perſon would diſſwade vs from a godly &amp; deuout courſe, let vs ſay to<note place="margin">Ruth. 1. 16. 17.</note> them with <hi>Ruths</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Intreat me not to leaue religion, nor to depart from it, for whither it goeth, I will go; and where it dwelleth I will dwell:</hi> the true profeſſours of it, ſhall be my<note place="margin">Thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, my people.</note> companions, <hi>God,</hi> the Author thereof, <hi>ſhall be my God, where it</hi> reſteth, <hi>will I</hi> reſt, <hi>and there will I die:</hi> the <hi>Lord doe ſo to me, and more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13647:7"/> alſo, if ought but death depart it and me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt theſe examples are very pregnant, and doe giue liuely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to ſerue God, if we be alone. But (my Lord) is it not grieuous to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> did not <hi>Eliah</hi> ſorrow, and vexe his ſpiritat this, that he was left alone, yea and deſired therefore to die?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>True it is, that Salomon ſaith, woe to<note place="margin">Anſwer to the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> him that is alone, but alone without helpe from the Lord: but this his children want neuer finally, the Lord is with them, and if he be their familiar friend, they may with <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay, We care not what man can doe vnto vs, for the Lord is on our ſide. By him more is with vs then againſt vs; this <hi>Eliſha</hi> being alone ſaw, and prayed that his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Gehezi</hi> might ſee: &amp; albeit <hi>Eliah</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to himſelfe to be alone, yet was he not alone, God was with him, and 7000. not ſeene, who bowed not their knee vnto <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al:</hi> and whereas he wiſhed to die for bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence of men, it was his weakenes, in which the Lord did ſhew mercy, and affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him comfort afterward; the like mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy may we expect, as holy martyrs haue experienced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Doth it not derogate (<hi>Renowned Duke</hi>) from your greatneſſe, to profeſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13647:7"/> from all nations in religion, and<note place="margin">Preuention of an obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> from all Iſrael, though they doe follow their forefathers, which were beyond the flood, and in Egypt ſeruing ſtrange Gods?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Albeit God hath exalted me here <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">doctrine. </seg>The ſecond</label> vpon earth, to rule ouer his people Iſrael, and though I ſucceede their vnmatchable Moſes, that man of God, yet iudge I true religion to be my chiefe honour, and to differ from all men differing from their way wherein they ſhould walke towards God, to be my glory: therefore is it that I ſay, <hi>But I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord,</hi> euen I <hi>Ioſua,</hi> though Duke, though Prince in Iſrael, and a guide to Gods people, I will with my family ſerue him, who hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me this great mercy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>You haue great cauſe to bleſſe God, that you in ſuch glory, haue ſo great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in ſo great proſperity ſuch zeale. It is rare for men of note to entertaine religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but moſt rare for ſuch therein to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſingular.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Such as truely ſeeke God in heart <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
                  </label> without hypocriſie, whatſoeuer their eſtate be, they hold it a ſpeciall duty to do ſeruice vnto God, &amp; that they can be in no eſtate, be it neuer ſo glorious with men, but that religion and the grace of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13647:8"/> maketh the ſame more glorious. By <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> deuotion in true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we become Saints on earth, we haue the fruit of the ſpirit, the earneſt and aſſurance of our adoption. By <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſenſible life are we better then things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, and are but equall with beaſts: by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> reaſon we are better then theſe, but no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Heathen: by religion, though falſe, are we worſhippers of a diuine power, and therin more then Sauages; but by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are we Chriſtians, and by ſincerity therin with religious practiſe, are we more then common Chriſtians, euen true and liuely members of Chriſt, in whom we are Gods adopted children, righteous before him: we haue inward peace of conſcience, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and outward grace by the approbation of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the godly, Angels are giuen to attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> vs, who are the children of the great King: Heauen is our inheritance, we haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſeats prepared, and ſhall with Chriſt iudge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the whole earth, and with him enioy the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> happineſſe for euer, when the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wicked ſhall be tormented world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>The weight of theſe reaſons may force any man to hold religion and ſincere walking with God, to be a grace vnto him, be he neuer ſo mightie in this world. He
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13647:8"/> hath here honour, and men attend him, but by a holy conuerſation he hath honor with God Alſufficient, &amp; Angels wait vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Here a man hath wealth, but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious holines, he hath an euerlaſting tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, and a ſupplie of all wants by grace. Here hath he, as a man, his pleaſures and delights, but by deuout ſeruing of God, he hath peace which paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that which the eie hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, nor the heart of a naturall man able to comprehend. Therefore ought we <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> in what glory ſo euer we be before men, to adde religion to our ſtate, and iudge it our crowne and glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Els may we rightly be iudged with <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                  </label> out it, no better then Heathen, rich Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, honourable Atheiſts, &amp; if men haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> delights without pietie, they be but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Epicures, which things indure not: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and without Gods good mercy, men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace quaile by that very ſame thing whereby among men they be of higheſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation. <hi>Achitophels</hi> policie ouerthrew him: <hi>Abſoloms</hi> beauty brought him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: <hi>Hamans</hi> honor was his ruine. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious feare of God is mans ſtay in euery <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> earthly eſtate; els the higher he is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, &amp; the more he poſſeſſeth without reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13647:9"/> the worſe he is, fartheſt from God, and nigher to confuſion. <hi>I</hi> therefore <hi>and my houſe will ſerue the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Mee thinke (Sir) by adding theſe<note place="margin">And my houſe. The grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</note> words, <hi>my houſe,</hi> in your ſpeech, you inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate your care to haue other religious, as well as your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>True it is you ſay, I now deſire as did my Maſter <hi>Moſes, Would to God all the people could prophecie.</hi> Indeede rather then God be vnſerued, a man ought alone to ſerue the Lord, this is his <hi>feruencie &amp; zeale</hi> to God; but true grace reſts not in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> of a true beleeuer, as gold in a nigards cheſt, but ſprouteth forth to the benefit of other, for he deſireth to make other like himſelfe, this is his <hi>compaſſion and loue.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>I am able to avouch this from my <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
                  </label> owne feeling, bleſſed be God, and I find it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> true in that worthy Apoſtle who ſaith, <hi>My</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>hearts deſire and prayer to God is for Iſrael that they may be ſaued:</hi> who after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion did labour in the Lords vineyard with vndurable paines to bring men vnto God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> So ought all of vs to doe in our places: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                  </label> the Lord commandes it, <hi>Returne &amp; cauſe other to returne;</hi> &amp; our Sauiour ſaid to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Peter, When thou art conuerted ſtrengthen thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezec. 18. 33 Luk. 22. 32.</note>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13647:9"/> 
                  <hi>brethren.</hi> The hatred of ſinne ſhould mooue vs where we may, to roote it out, the griefe which we ought to take, when we ſee men to ſinne, ſhould cauſe vs as far forth as wee be able to reclaime them, and not <hi>ſuffer ſin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leu. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>to reſt vpon them.</hi> That we ought to grieue for ſinne in our ſelues, ſo for the ſame in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 136.</note> wee ſee by <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe eyes guſhed out riuers of water, at the ſight of other men breaking Gods law. Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> wept<note place="margin">Luk. 19. 41. Ier. 13.</note> ouer Ieruſalem, <hi>Ieremies</hi> ſoule mourned in ſecret, S, <hi>Paul</hi> writ with teares; ſhall we haue a paſſion for ſinne committed, and not vſe meanes to haue it amended?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>He that is truely touched with the ſight of ſinne, cannot poſſibly neglect the meanes to winne men from ſinne. It is the nature of griefe to manifeſt it ſelfe, and workes in man an endeauour, to vſe means to haue the cauſe of grief taken away. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if wee truely grieue that men offend God, wee will not ſuffer them to goe on in ſinne, if we may amend it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>And as griefe may mooue vs, ſo the conſideration of the ſinners miſery, may enduce vs to care for their ſaluation. The ſinner is <hi>Sathans</hi> ſlaue, ſubiect to wrath, the heire of confuſion, who may daily looke for damnation and vengeance; oh, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13647:10"/> can but pitty a man in ſo great miſery? is he not mercileſſe and cruell that ſeeth one in a deadly danger, and may releeue him, and yet will not? Can wee ſee a man hanging himſelfe, ſtand by, and not cutte the cord? Can we beholde one running into a pit to drowne himſelfe, and if we may, not holde him backe? Theſe be mercileſſe cruelties, if ſo we ſhould neglect our brothers bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life: and it is no leſſe hardneſſe of heart to ſuffer men by ſinne, if it lie in vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them, to runne headlong to hell, where they ſhall hang in torments, and be drowned in the gulfe of perdition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Condemnation mercileſſe belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> to ſuch as will ſhew no mercy, it is true touching ſoule and body. No doubt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> holy men iudged rightly of this, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did diſcharge their duty herein. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> our Forefather taught his houſholde; <hi>Dauid</hi> the King was ſo minded, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to teach Gods waies vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 23.</note> that ſinners might be conuerted vnto the Lord. <hi>Philip</hi> we ſee ſought out <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> &amp; brought him to Chriſt; and the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Samaria</hi> did runne haſtily for her neighbors to behold the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> all which are written for our learning, that wee by their examples ſhould doe the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13647:10"/>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>A man would thinke that enough were ſaid to ſtirre vp one to care for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but for that men herein are too remiſſe, and indeed profeſſe a careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this with cruell <hi>Cain; What, am I my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>brothers keeper?</hi> I will the longer ſtay vpon this point, as a matter of abſolute neceſſity, the neglect wherof is the cauſe of ſo great encreaſe of wickedneſſe at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. It is the fruit of loue in the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and holy fellowſhip of Saints: One <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> article of our Creed is to beleeue this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but we by no mutuall care ſhew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſpirituall coniunction. The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body in the bodily communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe teach vs this, where euery member careth for the welfare of each other, and if any one be out of ioynt, all with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeeke to bring it in againe. The bodily fellowſhip worketh this mutual compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which keepeth the body in welfare; ſo ought our ſpiritual ioyning together work the like commiſeration towards euery er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, to keepe the Church in peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>You haue here from a naturall worke, plainely ſet out our duty in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall action: nature forceth the one, and therefore grace I hope will ſet vs forward to the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13647:11"/>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>If this ſuffice not, let this mooue vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that our not ſeeking to ſaue them, in our place, is to make our ſelues guilty of their ſin, he that is ſilent conſenteth, &amp; he that conſents is worthie of death, Rom. 1. 31. He is acceſſarie to treaſon who knoweth it, and reuealeth it not: ſinne is rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, we muſt attach the partie, at leaſt by a brotherly rebuke, leſt we let him eſcape, as Achab let goe Benadad, and his ſinne be made our tranſgreſſion, and ſo procure vnto our ſelues death. Againe, let <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the enlarging Chriſts kingdome incite vs to this duty, yea the great reward and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> which belongeth to him that ſaueth a ſoule, <hi>he ſhall couer the multitude of ſinnes,</hi> he<note place="margin">Iam. 5. Dan. 12. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhal ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer.</hi> The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> care of ſauing a ſoule, and the goodneſſe of<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 16.</note> the worke mooued God the Father to giue his onely Sonne to die, and Chriſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> himſelfe was willing to ſuffer great and vnſpeakeable torments to bring a poore ſinner vnto ſafetie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>If neither the commandement of God, the griefe of heart for ſinne, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners<note place="margin">Abriefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> miſery, holy mens exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, the bond of fellowſhip &amp; mutuall communion, our own danger in the neglect hereof, the care to enlarge Chriſts kingdom, the reward of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13647:11"/> happines, nor the loue of god, nor Chriſts ſufferings, can mooue vs to doe our beſt to ſaue a poore ſinner; let the deuill teach vs to look vnto it, who with his members ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly endeauonr to draw men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; to bring them to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If he &amp; his be ſo forward to ill, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward whereof is death, why ſhould not we do more to oppoſe him &amp; his inſtruments for mans life and ſaluation? eſpecially mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in feeding their flocke, who are charged to do it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their loue to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 21. 15. 16. 17. 2. Tim. 4. 1. 2 Ezec. 33. 8. Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies ſhold tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h their houſhold.</note> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their alleageance to their ſoueraigne, to avoid blood guiltines, and to preuent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall vengeance: And nothing leſſe are gouernours of families tied thereunto, they ſee &amp; blame, and not vnworthily, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that neglect their flocke: but they find not the ſame fault in themſelues for careleſſe omitting the inſtruction of their family, which they be in their own perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                  </label> as much bound to diſcharge, as a miniſter is to feed his flock; the Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> miniſters cure, ſo the family is the maſters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> charge, wherein the chiefe of the houſe, the<note place="margin">Deut. 5. 7. Eph. 6. 4. 1. Cor. 14. 35 Gen. 18. 19. 2. Tim. 1. 5. with 3. 15.</note> father, the mother, the maſter and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is to teach their children and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold in the waies of God. So are they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, ſo examples teach them to doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13647:12"/>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt truly ſpoken (Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Caleb</hi>) for we that haue charge of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are commanded to informe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; euen neceſſitie to keepe a holy vnity among vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſhould hereto perſwade vs, how elſe can there be peace, if the <hi>Lambe</hi> and the <hi>Lyon</hi> dwell together, a <hi>Cain</hi> and an <hi>Abel,</hi> a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and faithfull <hi>Iſaac,</hi> a ſcorning <hi>Michol,</hi> &amp; a zealous <hi>Dauid?</hi> How can mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters reforme whole Aſſemblies, if we do not our endeauour to help them in our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies? This want of priuate helpe maketh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the publike miniſtery ſo vnprofitable, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly it is. The whole burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of care for ſoules is laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſters ſhoulders, when a priuate watch is impoſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, &amp; houſhold inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon euery faithful &amp; religious Gouernour of a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Therefore families haue bin called the Churches of God, wherein God was, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ought to be worſhipped with holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes. And how can a maſter be a dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall head, and let his members periſh? The diuell ſo much oppoſing it, mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſo much diſtaſting it, all ſo vſually <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> neglecting it, doe declare it ſufficiently to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> be a moſt holy and worthy worke to be carefully vndertaken, and with all good conſcience performed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Vndoubtedly, if the benefit which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13647:12"/> hence would ariſe, firſt to our ſelues, to our children and houſhold, then to the help of the publike miniſtery, were well weighed, there be none that haue either care of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, wiſh well to their children, deſire faithfulneſſe in their ſeruants, and couet to ſee Ieruſalem in proſperity, but they would betake them ſpeedily to this ſo great, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and godly a worke. How come chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> often to deſtruction, but by parents negligence in their religious education? If we bring them vp well, wee may by Gods mercie preuent their ill ende: if wee vſe meanes, and they periſh, yet our ſoules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort, that we are no way guilty: whereas otherwiſe the childe may ſay: Wo is me, and wo to you my parents, who haue neglected my education: and parents may anſwer, Wo to vs our ſonne therefore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee now ſo miſerable, and our ſelues hereby ſo vncomfortable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I therfore and my houſe,</hi> by Gods help, <hi>will ſerue the Lord,</hi> as God hath giuen mes grace to ſee and know the euill, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to preuent it in me and mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Your ſpeech in the order thereof teacheth mee, as I take it, not onely your care herein to do what you ought, but your wiſdome in an orderly proceeding therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13647:13"/>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>It is well noted of you: I ſet my ſelfe <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> before my houſhold, becauſe the head lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth firſt the body, before the body can mooue by the members to performe any office. So it is in the naturall conſtitution of a body, ſo in the politicall gouernment of the common wealth, let Princes leade, the people will follow, for from the head <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> commeth life &amp; motion to the body. And the ſame order is to bee obſerued in well guiding of a family. There is litle hope to finde a godly family, where the maſter is either careleſſe, or prophane. He muſt ſet on and go before, if he intend to haue the reſt good. His life is of authority, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample draweth other to him, his words are of force, and in doing his duty may he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>I doe perſwade my ſelfe, that ſome haue good deſires hereunto, &amp; more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes by this may bee ſet forward to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle their houſholds in order: but euery one that gladly would doe well, know not how to doe ſo; therefore let me obtaine (moſt Noble Lord) the knowledge of 3. things at your hands, both for mine owne, and the peoples inſtruction herein. I. How a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily<note place="margin">Three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</note> may bee at the firſt religiouſly plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? II. How a family irreligious may be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13647:13"/> reformed? III. How it may be ſo kept, and preſerued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Three neceſſary queſtions propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and worthy to be anſwered. To ſatisfie you in the firſt. To plant a family in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">Anſwer to the firſt. How a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily may be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> feare of God. I. Parents muſt bring vp ſuch children well, with which they will build vp a houſe, acquaint them with the Lords will, with duties of a husband and wife, of a father and mother, and ſo marry in iudgement, before they marry, and not in carnall luſt. Without knowledge of the former chriſtian duties, mens mariages are but Turkiſh, and to marry in the latter on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is ſenſual &amp; brutiſh. II. Parents muſt ſee that the parties to be maried be fitted, that their be no diſlike in affection, nor iarre in religion, but that the marriage be made in loue, and ſetled in Gods feare; both belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, both imbracing one &amp; the ſame truth, as neere as may be. <hi>Abraham</hi> doth fetch a <hi>Rebecca</hi> for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> from his fathers houſe, &amp; there is religion; when <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> taking an <hi>Athalia</hi> for his ſonne, bringeth into his houſe idolatry and ſuperſtition. To plant religion, wee muſt bring in religion into a family, by education, and by a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of them togither in the feare of God. III. and laſtly, Parents muſt care
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13647:14"/> that the religious perſons, religiouſly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, bee religiouſly ſerued. And therfore, that ſuch as become ſeruants to them, bee of the ſame holy profeſſion with them, and of like conuerſation. And thus may a family be planted religiouſly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>What direction giue you for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>viz.</hi> to reforme a diſordered family?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>The gouernour muſt do, as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king<note place="margin">Anſwer to the ſecond queſtion. How a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily may be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> a new houſe, where an olde ſtood; hee muſt remooue the old wholly as far forth as it is vnprofitable, and make the reſt all new. The man and the wife muſt be ſound, they bee the two ſide poſts; ſo their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who are as the beames laid ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart, if they be rotten, though all the reſt be new, at the length the worke will fall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>How muſt they be made ſound, if they be rotten?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>By repenting of all former ſin, and negligence paſt, and by vndertaking this work ſincerely with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant durablenes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>What timber is ſo rotten, as wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſerue to be put in the new building?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Euery one that perſiſts in euill, and will not be reformed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>But what if there be ſome ſuch, whom the maſter of the family cannot caſt out?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Let ſuch ſo be in the houſe, as they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13647:14"/> beare no rule in it, neither any ſound part depend or ſtay vpon them; ſo ſhall there be neither breach nor ruine thereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>What other meanes is there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme by?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Secondly, the gouernour muſt bring all his houſhold in ſubiection to Gods word, to heare and attend vnto the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miniſterie thereof, as the ordinarie meanes to reclame men. It is the power of<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18. Heb 4. 12. Pſal 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9 9. Pro. 2. 11. 12. 16. The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> God to ſaluation, it is mighty in operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it cleanſeth our waies, and keepeth vs from all euill. Thirdly, he muſt ſet vp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his houſe religious exerciſes; theſe make publike meanes more profitable, more highly to be eſteemed, and the iudgement better to be ſetled; euill hereby is preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yea thruſt out from the family, bad perſons hereby are tried and found out, the well diſpoſed made more religious, and God not a litle glorified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>What are the holy exerciſes which you here ſpeake of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Reading of the holy Scriptures, the voice of God, Catechiſing, telling ſome ſhort ſtorie of ſome notable example in the word, making vſe thereof, ſinging of pſalmes, and when the publike ſermon hath bin heard, to repeate therof as much as is remembred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13647:15"/>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>This, ſay ſome, will make ſeruants wearie, and none will come to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>It were better to be without ſeruants then haue ſuch as hate goodneſſe, but this ſame which is obiected, and ſo much fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may be anſwered eaſily, and the feare taken away. The maſter to hold vp ſuch good exerciſes, and not to wearie his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, muſt I. be towards all his ſeruants mercifull, in giuing them a time to reſt, not to dogge them day and night to their labour, as beaſts. II. He muſt performe al things ſeaſnably, not late in the night after toylſome labour, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wearines &amp; time it ſelfe doe inforce the body to ſleepe. III. He muſt not haue the ſame exerciſes held long, at one time, but auoid tedious pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, leaſt one be ſpeaking, whilſt the reſt be ſleeping; as it falleth out ſometime by the weakneſſe of one, &amp; the zealous indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an other. IV. He muſt regard much a religious ſeruant, reward him well, and pray to God for ſuch, &amp; he ſhall not want godly ſeruants, and be well rid of the lewd and prophane.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caleb.</speaker>
               <p>If ſeruants be encouraged, godly diſcretion be vſed, honeſt libertie graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, competent wages allowed, tollerable labour onely vrged, difference made, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13647:15"/> the beſt anſwerably rewarded, there is no doubt either of getting or retaining ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: but how may a family reformed ſo be preſerued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>I. The chiefe muſt themſelues keep <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> good orders eſtabliſhed; their neglect<note place="margin">Anſwer to the third queſtion. How to keepe in order a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> breeds in other careleſnes, their omiſſion occaſioneth in other tranſgreſſion. II. They muſt make knowne their ful reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all, in matters of religion, that they will walke vprightly in the midſt of the houſe, that they will allow no order to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> broken. III. They muſt ſee to offences<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> againſt God and religion more narrowly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> then iniuries done to themſelues, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and correct the one more, then the other, ſo doe they ſhew greater regard of God, then reſpect of themſelues. IV. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They muſt ſhew fauour to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> towardly, pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eaſily the firſt or ſecond offence, but not be remiſſe in puniſhing duly, where and when the fault and partie offending iuſtly deſerues correction; this is ſo to be courteous in loue and compaſſion, as an awefull hand may be kept ouer the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily with godly diſcretion. V. They <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> muſt caſt out the vile perſons, wilfull and<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> obſtinate, mocking Iſmaels may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with Iſaacs: a little leauen leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> the whole lumpe, one lewde perſon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13647:16"/> may doe much hurt. VI. They may not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> receiue in any knowne wicked perſon for feare of infection. VII. They muſt will <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> one to exhort another to a mutual emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of grace, louingly to admoniſh one an other, and to pray one for another. VIII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> They muſt keepe all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idlenes, the nurſe, or rather mother of all wickedneſſe, as of pride in apparell, waſtfull expences, vaine paſtimes, and other ſinnes of the fleſh to be abhorred among Chriſtians. IX. They <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> muſt performe mutuall duties one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, maſters to ſeruants, and theſe to their maſters, but chiefly the husband and wife muſt loue each other: if wrongs bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, let themſelues between the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or with the good liking of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſecret friend to both, be ended. They muſt beware that the houſhold become not partners in the matter; for ſeruants by ſlander, flattery, and whiſperings will kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the contention, and make a prey of them. The contending of man and wife muſt neuer want loue, but if any ſmite ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the tongue, both muſt ioine in one againſt the ſmiter. But to preuent this, let none faile to performe what is due to be done. Complaints ariſe firſt vpon neglect of duty, the performance whereof is the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13647:16"/> touchſtone of profeſſion: where the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is louing, the wife learnes obedience; where the wife is obedient, the husband is mooued to bee kinde, by their well liuing the houſe is preſerued in peace, and where they two do as they ought to themſelues &amp; their family, the children &amp; ſeruants learn to walk in ſubiection, and do in an awefull loue diſcharge their duties, and hereby do they prouoke one another vnto piety, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue loue and vnity in the ſpirit, and keep vp holy exerciſes with prayer. Laſtly, they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> muſt vpholde the publike miniſtery and preaching of the word, without which, by reaſon of the looſeneſſe of al other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who do not voluntarily take a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſe priuately, they can neuer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long in good order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>It remaines only now to giue ſome reaſons, why the ſeuerall ſorts in a family, and ſo that all therein ſhould be religious, as firſt why the father, maſter &amp; husband, which are all one perſon in the houſe, ſhould be religious?<note place="margin">Why the husband ſhould be religious. Deut. 6. Exod. 20. Epheſ. 6. 4.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>I. Becauſe he is ſpecially charged with inſtruction of the houſholde, and to ſee to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Secondly, becauſe the family hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him chiefly the name. Thirdly, becauſe he is the head. Fourthly, for a ſpeciall exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13647:17"/> as moſt forcible to draw other on. Fiftly, becauſe of the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of good gouernors of families, as <hi>Abraham, Cornelius,</hi> &amp; other. Sixtly, for that he ſhall anſwer for his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, as the miniſter for his flock. Seuenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to bring a bleſſing vppn his children.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould the wife, mother, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of the family be religious?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe ſhe is the husbands ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,<note place="margin">Why the wife ſhould be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> or rather picture to repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him in al good things, and as the moone doth from the ſunne, ſo ſhe is to receiue her light from him, which ſhe alſo is to let ſhine out to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, becauſe ſhe is to be an help to her husband; now ſhe can be in nothing more a helpe, then in being with him reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to further his inſtructions taught to his houſhold. Thirdly, for that the husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is often from home, &amp; ſhee is to ſupply his place, to ſee the houſhold kept in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Fourthly, for mutuall peace ſake; if ſhe bee not religious, ſhee will oppoſe him, as a mocking <hi>Michol,</hi> or as an idolatrus <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> cauſe him to forſake the worſhippe of the tru God. Fiftly, becauſe godly wiues are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for religion in ſcripuure, which are to be followed. Sixtly, becauſe ſhee is the firſt that inſtructs the child, as being moſt with it, cauſing it to vnderſtand that which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13647:17"/> ſhe doth pleaſe to teach it. Seuenthly, for that ſhe beeing fraile by nature, and apt without grace to goe aſtray herſelfe, may ſooner, as vſually it commeth to paſſe, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the child then the father, by being ſo continually with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Why ought childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be religious?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, for their godly parents ſake.<note place="margin">Why chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> Secondly, becauſe they bee the ſecond linke in a family, and ſo in the middle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the higheſt and loweſt; they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore next Parents muſt be religious, that ſeruants by them grow not vicious. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for their fathers ioy, whoſe true &amp; ſure comfort is not that their children can hunt, ſo could prophane <hi>Eſau;</hi> nor that they be faire; ſo was <hi>Abſolom</hi> beautifull, &amp; came to anill end; nor that they be in Honour; ſo was <hi>Saul</hi> a caſt-way; nor great Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſo were <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes who periſhed in their ſinnes: but euen becauſe they be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, for the grace of God endureth euer. Fourthly, for a bleſſing vnto themſelues, as God hath promiſed to all that feare him. Fiftly, for encouragement vnto their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, beholding grace in them, which will cauſe them to continue gracious, leſt their children loſe grace. Sixtly: becauſe they preſerue the good name vpon their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13647:18"/> get them honour, and are a crowne of glory to them, euen after death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Why ought ſeruants to be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>1. For their maſters praiſe. 2. For<note place="margin">Why ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ought to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> their owne comfort. 3. Becauſe good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants are recorded in Scripture for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake. 4. Becauſe whileſt they be mens ſeruants, they may bee the Lords free men by religion. 5. To doe their ſeruice ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, as looking for reward from God. 6. For childrens good, whome leud ſeruants may eaſily miſleade.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>So then, all ought to be religious, that the maſter with his whole family may be ſaid to ſerue the Lord, as thou haſt (moſt noble <hi>Ioſua</hi>) promiſed this day for thy ſelfe and thy houſholde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>So it is, and great is that bleſſing, where all become the Lords true ſeruants, religion their practiſe, the holy word their guide: there man and wife are brother and ſiſter, parents &amp; children of ſpirituall kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and haue one father: maſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants mutuall members &amp; co-heires with Chriſt Ieſus: there haue they one voice in prayer with deuotion, one care to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſuperſtition. All performe mutuall duties; one ſeeketh to pleaſe another, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13647:18"/> hold loue, to keepe peace, and to preſerue a holy communion in charitie with pietie. One diſtruſteth not another, one wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not another, there is a godly ſtriuing together, who ſhall doe the beſt to pleaſe God. They beare with weakneſſes, they ioy in each others goodneſſe; here they deſire peace of conſcience, the fellowſhip of the godly; Gods glorie they doe ayme at: the world they liue in, but euer with deſire of heauen, which God hath promiſed to all that walke righteouſly before him, and ſerue him; which grace the Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe vs now and euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>Amen, Amen. But yet (Sir) before we end, I beſeech you commend to my meditation ſome ſpeciall Scriptures to ſtir me vp vnto deuotion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioſ.</speaker>
               <p>If it pleaſe you for the godly mans <hi>bleſſedneſſe,</hi> reade Pſal. 1. for his <hi>comfort,</hi> Pſal. 37. Heb. 12. for his <hi>holy deſires</hi> to Gods word, and his obedience, Pſal. 119. for his <hi>religious practiſe,</hi> Iob. 31. Rom. 12. Heb. 13. for his <hi>faith,</hi> Heb. 11. for his <hi>loue,</hi> 1. Cor. 13. and for the effectuall markes of his <hi>vocation,</hi> and eternall <hi>ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Rom. 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you humbly, and bleſſe God for you, whome I beſeech to proſper
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13647:19"/> theſe things to our comfort, and that they may further vs to a holy practiſe, to the praiſe of the God of Iſrael, that we may be found the Iſrael of God in the laſt day.</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13647:19"/>
            <head>The Catechiſme.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow many things are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for you to vnderſtand, that you may know both God and your ſelfe?</head>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Theſe ſixe things: I. rightly to conceiue of God what he is, by his word and workes: II. to vnderſtand the creation: III. mans miſerie by the fall. IV. our redemption: V. our ſanctification. VI. the certaintie of our glorification.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of God.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Who made you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> God. Eſa. 42. 5. Gen. 1. 26, 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What a one is God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> God is a ſpirit, Ioh. 4. 24. holy, Exod. 15. 11. Iuſt, 2. Chron. 12. 6. and mercifull, Exod. 34. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How many Gods are there?</head>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13647:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> But onely one God, Deut. 6. 4. yet three perſons, Mat. 3. 16. 1. Ioh. 5. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which are the three Perſons?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The Father begetting, the Son be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and the holy Ghoſt proceeding, 2. Cor. 13. 13. Mat. 28. 19. and theſe three are God, Ioh. 1. 1. 1. Ioh. 5. 7. Act. 5. 3. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which of theſe three became man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſecond Perſon, Ieſus Chriſt both God and man, Eſa. 9. 6. Heb. 2. 17.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of our Creation.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Of what did God make man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> His bodie was of duſt, the woman of <hi>Adams</hi> ribbe, Gen. 2. 7. 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What a one did God make them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> He made them both good, Gen. 1. 31. holy and righteous, Gen. 1. 26. Eph. 4. 24. Coloſ. 3. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What was then mans eſtate and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It was the ſtate of innocencie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne or miſerie, and to God was he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, Gen. 1. 27. 31. &amp; 2. 25. &amp; 1. 28.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of mans fall and miſerie.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are you now ſuch a one by birth, as he was by creation?</head>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13647:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Alas no: I am by nature full of ſin, Pſal. 51. 5. Iob 25. 4, 5, 6. Rom. 3. from verſ. 9. to 19. And ſo moſt miſerable, Iob 14. 1. 2. Rom. 5. 14. Eph. 2. 1, 2, 3. Rom. 3. 23. &amp; 2. 8. 9. And to God deteſtable, Pſalm. 11. 5. Gal. 3. 10. Mat. 7. 23. &amp; 25. 41.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is ſinne?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The breaking of Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by thought, word, or deed, 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How many commandements are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Tenne, Deut. 10. 4. diuided into two Tables, Deut. 4. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which be the Commaundements?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c. Exod. 20. Deut. 5. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Doe theſe tenne commaund or forbid no more but onely what there is ſet downe in ſhew?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes: they command or forbidde all the kindes contained vnder the ſameth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng mentioned, and all the cauſes, with occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereunto, 1. Ioh. 3. 15. Mat. 5. 28. 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are they a prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No, nor ſo to bee vſed: they are a rule for me to liue after, and doe teach mee my duty to God and my neighbour, Deut. 6. &amp; 31. 12. Pſalm. 119. 105. Eccleſ. 12. 13. Mat. 22. 37. 39.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is your duty towards God?</head>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13647:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> My duty towards God, is to beleeue in him, to feare him, and to loue him, &amp;c. 2. Chro. 20. 20. Eccl. 12. 13. Mat. 22. 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is your duty toward your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is to loue my neighbour as my ſelfe, &amp;c. Mat. 22. 39. Rom. 13 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Can you keepe the Commaundements, and not offend God, or your neighbour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: I breake them euery day in thought, word, &amp; deed, hating both God, and my neighbour by nature, Pſal. 14. 1, 2, 3. Rom. 8. 7. &amp; 1. 30. 2. Cor. 3. 5. Tit. 3. 3,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is then now your eſtate, and what deſerue you by thus offending God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am in the ſtate of corruption, and doe deſerue Gods curſe, which is eternall deſtruction of body and ſoule. Deu. 27. 26. Mat. 25. 41. 46. Gal. 3. 10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of mans redemption.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are you in this caſe to doe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To cry vnto God for mercy, &amp; ſeeke for deliuerance. Luk. 15. 17. Pſ. 51. 1. 2. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are you of your ſelfe able, or is there any good in you to mooue God to ſet you free?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No indeed: Rom. 3. 10. &amp; 7. 18. Luk. 17. 10. 2. Cor. 4. 4. Ephe. 2. 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13647:21"/>
                  <head>Q. Then who doth redeeme you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Onely Ieſus Chriſt. Rom. 7. 25. 2. Cor. 5. 21. Rom. 5. 19. Gal. 2. 20. &amp; 3. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is Ieſus Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> He is the eternal Sonne of God. Mat. 17. 5. Heb. 1. 23, a King to gouerne vs, Pſa. 2. 6. Mat. 28. 18. a Prieſt to offer for vs, Pſ. 110. 4. &amp; a Prophet to teach vs, Deut. 18. 18. Eſa. 51. 1. Mat. 17. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What beleeue you concerning him in the Articles of the Creede?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I doe beleeue that he was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is this to you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I do perſwade my ſelfe hereby, that his puritie is for my corruption, his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for my tranſgreſſion, his death for my debt, and his aſcenſion for my eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. 1. Cor. 1. 30. Phil. 3. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. But as God made all, will ſo Ieſus Chriſt alſo ſaue all?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No verily, many ſhall bee damned, few ſhall be ſaued, Mat. 7. 13. 14. Onely the elect, which take hold of Chriſt by a liuely faith. Ioh. 3. 16. 36. Mar. 16. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is this liuely faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a true perſwaſion of my heart, grounded vpon Gods promiſes. Eph. 3. 17 Rom. 4. 21. that Ieſus Chriſt is giuen to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13647:22"/> me, Ioh. 3. 16. and the merits of his death and paſſion, are as truly mine, as if I my ſelf had wrought them, 2. Cor. 5. 21. Rom. 8. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How come you by this faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> From my effectuall calling by the word preached, &amp; the worke of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Act. 13. 48. Rom. 10. 14, 15. Eph. 1. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Where is ſet downe the ſumme of your beleefe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> In my Creed, <hi>I beleeue in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almightie, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are theſe a prayer, or ſo to be vſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: it teacheth me what to beleeue concerning God and his Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What good hath Gods Church, the true beleeuers, aboue the reſt of mankinde?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> They are in the ſtate of grace, they haue communion with Chriſt, &amp; one with another, the forgiuenes of ſinnes, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection of the body, and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Sanctification.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How may it appeare, that you haue this faith, and alſo theſe benefits?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By my ſanctification.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Who doth ſanctifie you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The holy Ghoſt, Rom. 15. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q And what is ſanctification?</head>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13647:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a making new of the whole man, whereby he daily dieth to ſin, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, Eph. 4. 23. 24 Gal. 5. 24. 1. Theſſ. 4. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What grace proceeds from this ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> True repentance, leauing that which is ill with hatred, and performing new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with gladneſſe of heart continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Ier. 31. 19. Act. 26. 20. Pſal. 119. 10. 14. 34. 35. 44. 113. 115. 136.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What eſtate ſtand you in, beeing ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and penitent?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am in the bleſſed eſtate of grace, wherein if I continue, I ſhal inherit eternall life, Tit. 3. 4, 5, 6, 7. Rom. 11. 12. 2. Tim. 4. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why hath God thus made, redeemed, ſanctified, and hitherto preſerued you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſerue him truly all the daies of my life, Eph. 2. 10. Tit. 2. 11. 12. Luk. 1. 74 75.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How muſt God be ſerued?</head>
                  <p>A. Onely after his will reuealed in his written word, Deut. 30. 8. 10. and 4. 2. 2. Cor. 4. 6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of our ſtrengthening in the ſtate of grace, for the certaintie of our glorification.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13647:23"/>
                  <head>Q. Is it needfull for ſuch as are elected, and once called, iuſtified, and ſanctified, that they ſhould continue ſtil in vſing meanes to ſaluation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yea truely: elſe they will fall away, Pro. 29. 18. 2. Chro. 15. 2. Heb. 3. 12. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things muſt you continue in to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelfe of ſaluation, and to grow ſtrong in the way of life?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I. In the knowledge of Gods word, Pſal. 1. 2. Act. 2. 42. 2. Pet. 1. 19. Ioh. 10. 27. 28. II. In faith, Ioh. 3. 36. III. In loue to the godly, Ioh. 13. 35. 1, Ioh. 3. 14. IV. In obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Eze. 36. 26. Pſa. 15. 5. Ier. 32. 39, 40. V. In patient ſuffering for Chriſt, Rom. 8. 17. Iam. 1. 12. VI. In alonging after Chriſts comming, 2. Tim. 4. 8. VII. In ſincerity without hypocriſie, which will appeare by my appealing to God in theſe things, Ioh. 21. 15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sacraments.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Hath God giuen any helpes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded further any other meanes beſides the word, for the ſtrengthening of vs herein?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes, theſe two: Sacraments &amp; praier.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is a Sacrament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> An outward ſigne and ſeale of inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible graces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How do the Sacraments ſtrengthen you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By a reuerent vſing and meditating
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13647:23"/> of them rightly vnderſtood, as ſignes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting Chriſt and his benefits, and ſure ſeales of his couenant with vs. Gen. 9. 9. to 18. and 17. 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How many Sacraments are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Only two: Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, 1. Cor. 10. 1, 2, 3, 4. Mat. 28. 19. and 26. 26, 27. 1. Cor. 11. 23, 24 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ſigne and thing ſignified in Baptiſme?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſigne is water, and the grace is the blood of Chriſt, by which I am waſhed from my ſinnes. Act. 2. 38. and 22. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the ſignes and things ſignified in the Lords Supper?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A</label> The ſignes are the bread and wine; the things ſignified are the body &amp; blood of Chriſt. 1. Cor. 11, 23, 24, 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why come you to receiue?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſtrengthen my faith, and to keepe in remembrance Chriſt his death, till his comming again, Rom. 4. 11. 1. Cor. 11. 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What ought you to doe before you come?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Prepare my ſelfe by examination, 1. Cor. 11. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What ought you to come with, to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> With 4. things. 1. Knowledge both of my miſery, Gods mercy, &amp; the doctrine of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13647:24"/> the Sacrament. II. With faith in Ieſus Chriſt, Heb. 11. 6. III. VVith repentance for all my ſinnes, Eſa. 1. 10. 11. 14. 15. 16. Prou. 21. 27. IV. VVith heartie loue vnto my neighbour, Math. 5. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What if you come vnprepared without theſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I come vnworthy, I am guilty of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, 1. Cor. 11. 27. I doe eate and drinke my owne damnation, verſe 29. God may puniſh me, verſe 40. and the diuell may enter into me, as he did into <hi>Iudas,</hi> and bring me to deſtruction of body and ſoule, Ioh. 13. 27.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a right hearty, and faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt made vnto God, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, 1. Ioh. 5. 14. Rom. 8. 26. Iam. 1. 6. Ioh. 14. 14. and 15. 16. Math. 3. 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Can or doth euery one pray, that vttereth words, and vſeth a forme of prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No. It is a ſpeciall gift to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuch onely pray, as haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what to aske, a heartie deſire in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and faith to beleeue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What direction of prayer haue you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſame which our Sauiour Chriſt taught his diſciples, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13647:24"/>
                  <head>Q. What deſire you of God in this prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I deſire my Lord God our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, who is the giuer of all goodnes, to ſend his grace vnto mee, and to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that we may worſhippe him, ſerue him, and obey him, as wee ought to doe; and I pray vnto God, that hee will ſend vs all things that be needfull, both for our ſoules and bodies, and that hee will be mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs our ſinnes, and that it will pleaſe him to ſaue and defend vs in al dangers ghoſtly and bodily, and that he will keep vs from all ſinne and wickednes, and from our ghoſtly enemy, and from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting death. And this I truſt hee will do of his mercy and goodnes, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore I ſay, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm: Of new birth.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> WHat is your name?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Channanuel,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>God is gracious to vs.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Loue wholly the Lord with the heart.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Benalleuel,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>God is gracious to vs.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Loue wholly the Lord with the heart.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13647:25"/>
                  <head>Q. Who gaue you this name?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> My Godfathers and my Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who with my father, brought mee to the Miniſter, into the congregation, to be baptized, and were eſpeciall witneſſes of the ſame, and profeſſours of my faith and obedience to God for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why were you baptized?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I might receiue a badge of my Chriſtian religion, &amp; be admitted into the Church, to liue amongſt the profeſſors of Chriſts name, and to be receiued of them, and accompted as a member of Chriſt, the child of God, &amp; an inheritour of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, vntil I ſhew the contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Whereby may you now be certaine that you are ſuch a one in deede?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> If I doe what my Godfathers and Godmothers did make profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What did your Godfathers and Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make profeſſion of for you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> They did profeſſe three things in my name: the firſt was the forſaking of the Diuell, and all his workes, the pompes and the vanities of this wicked world, &amp; all the ſinfull luſts of the fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What, were you then bound to them, that you haue promiſed to forſake them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yea verily, I am a bondſlaue to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13647:25"/> by the corruption of my nature, prone to all vice, hauing the ſeede of all ſinne in me, and do hate both God and my neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How can you then forſake this wofull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and ceaſe from any euill, being thus bound and prone thereunto?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not by any naturall power, in, or of my ſelfe, but onely by the grace of God, when it is giuen vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are you ſure you haue forſaken them, are you not deceiued?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am not deceiued: for I hate vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly the workes of the diuell, the worlds vanity, all the vngodly manners of euery man: and I labour by all good meanes, to die to all ſin daily, louing the word of God, following it &amp; all godly examples, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to kill ſpeedily euery ill motion, but cheriſhing the good in my heart, by meditation, vowes, faſting, and prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. But can you tell me what are the works of the diuell, the worlds vanitie, and the ill mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the heart?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Whatſoeuer I, or any other, doe thinke, ſpeake, or doe, againſt the will of God, reuealed in his written word.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What hath mooued you to forſake the diuell, the world, and the fleſh?</head>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13647:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For that I haue learned, and do well perceiue, by knowledge from the word, &amp; mine owne experience, that theſe three be the onely malicious, ſpirituall, powerfull, ſubtill and continuall enemies of my eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the other two things, that your Godfathers and Godmothers made profeſſion of for you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> They ſecondly made profeſſion of my beliefe to all the twelue Articles of my Chriſtian faith: and thirdly, of my willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to learne diligently Gods holy will &amp; commandements, and to walke obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſame all the daies of my life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Where is this will of God to be learned?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not from mine owne fantaſie, mans wiſedome, traditions, or examples of men, but onely out of the Scripture, which is the word written by his Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, in the bookes of the old and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which is ſufficient to teach vs all things neceſſary, that we neede to beleeue for our ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What reaſons haue you to perſwade your ſelfe, that this Scripture which we holde, is the true word of God, and none other?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Firſt, from the pen-men, being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and moſt of them ſimple &amp; plaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13647:26"/> who doe mutually conſent, ſetting downe their owne faults without partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Secondly, from the matter, aboue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall mens reach; of mans creation, reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, laſt iudgement, and of the Trinity in vnity, prophecies alſo fulfilled in all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. Thirdly, from the manner of ſpeaking, peremptorily reproouing or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, without ſiniſter reſpects. Fourthly, from the effect, binding conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting men, to hate euen life it ſelfe for Gods glorie. Fifthly, the miraculous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation thereof, with puniſhment of ſuch as ſeeke to ouerthrow either it, or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours thereof. Laſtly, that it aſcribes all glory to God, the maine end that it ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth at.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What meanes muſt you vſe to come to the ſauing knowledge of Gods word?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. Daily reading. 2. Learning the Catechiſme, the grounds of religion. 3. hearing the Word with mind &amp; affection both read &amp; preached publikely, by Gods Miniſters. 4. Meditation in minde, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the doctrine gathered, &amp; in heart to affect the vſe made, after I haue either read or heard it. 5. Conference by asking of ſuperiours and Miniſters, by reaſoning with equals, and teaching inferiours, all in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13647:27"/> reuerence and humility, to vnderſtand that I know not, to be reſolued in that I doubt of, and to call to memorie what I haue forgotten. 6. Continuall prayer, with practiſe of it in my particular calling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Doe you thinke you are thus bound to forſake the diuell, the world, and the fleſh, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in God, to learne to know and doe his will, as they haue promiſed for you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes verily, and by Gods helpe ſo will I endeauour to doe, or elſe were I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull to God my Father, that hath called me into the ſtate of ſaluation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me his child; and alſo vnmindfull of my ſureties, that haue made ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. But tell me, how could any perſwade themſelues, that you ſhould doe as they haue made profeſſion for you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By beeing aſſured by faith, that the ſeede of the faithfull are bleſſed, they iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging me charitably to be one of them, did hope by the grace of God belonging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me in Chriſt, and through the meanes which ſhould be vſed, I would performe the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the meanes which ought to be vſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To be taught ſo ſoone as I ſhall
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13647:27"/> be able to learne, what a ſolemne profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I haue made by them. 2. To be exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to heare Sermons, and to learne all things which a Chriſtian ought to know for his ſoules health: but eſpecially the principles of religion, contained in theſe foure: the Creede, the Lords prayer, the tenne Commandements, and the doctrine of the Sacraments.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Let vs then ſee, whether theſe meanes haue beene vſed, and how you haue profited: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the articles of your beleefe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I beleeue in God the Father, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doe you chiefly learne out of theſe articles of your Chriſtian faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. I learne to beleeue that there is a God, to beleeue God, and alſo in him. 2. That he is but one in ſubſtance, yet diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into three, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, which diſtinction is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, property, and manner of working. 3. That this God hath a Church, to which onely he is truly knowne, and by the ſame ſincerely worſhipped.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How can you be perſwaded that there is a God?</head>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:13647:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. By his created workes declaring: 2. by my conſcience accuſing: 3. by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments terrifying: 4. by order obſerued in all things: 5. by heathen authors conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: 6. by the Scripture confidently auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is God we cannot tell, therefore tell me what a one he is?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> A ſpirituall ſubſtance, moſt holy, &amp; of glorious maieſtie; in finite in his beeing, as euery where preſent; in wiſedome, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing and rightly diſpoſing all things: in power, doing what he liſt; in iuſtice, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he will iuſtly; and in mercie, to ſaue whom he pleaſeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How doe you behold and conceiue of this God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not by any bodily ſhape, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, by his word, as he hath therein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted himſelfe, and by his workes of creation, preſeruation and gouerning eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, according to his foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and appointment therein, to his owne glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What beleeue you concerning God the Father?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God almighty, in order the firſt Perſon in the Trinity, begetting the Sonne from euerlaſting, of his whole
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13647:28"/> ſubſtance: maker of heauen and earth, men and angels, and all things elſe very good, onely by his word, of nothing, at the beginning, in ſixe daies, and ſtill by his prouidence preſerues the ſame, for my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What was man eſpecially made of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Man conſiſts of body and ſoule, the firſt mans body was made of the duſt of the earth, but our bodies come by genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are with his mortall: and both his and all our ſoules by inſpiration, and are immortall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What eſtate ſtood man in by creation, and what a one did God make him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> In the eſtate of innocency, void of all ſinne, free from any puniſhment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and was made after Gods Image, that is, holy and righteous, hauing perfect knowledge of God and his will, as much as was neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him, and alſo readineſſe of will in hearty affection, with bodily ſtrength to fulfill the ſame: and had withall the rule of all Gods creatures, made for his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How then come you into this wretched eſtate?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> my firſt parents, who wilfully diſobeyed God, by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13647:29"/> the diuels inticement, infidelity and pride poſſeſſing their hearts, and ſtood and fell in the roome of all mankinde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How can our ſoules be ſinfull, that come not by propagation, but by inſpiration?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. For that his ſoule was deputy for all ſoules of men naturally begotten. 2. Becauſe man ſinned, and man is not man, before body and ſoule bee knit togither, which being conioyned, become togither, as man, partaker of mans fall and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Doth any thing of that Image of God remaine yet in vs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes: 1. In the minde a certaine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall corrupt knowledge of nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning good and euill, to make vs inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable before God. 2. In the conſcience a power to reprooue and repreſſe in part vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled affections. 3. In will, though a free, yet a weake choice, in euery naturall and ciuill action.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What euils doe we receiue by this fall?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. In the mind ignorance of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, vnaptneſſe to learne them, or to iudge of them aright; but apt to learn euill, and to inuent the ſame. 2. In conſcience impureneſſe to excuſe ſinne, not to accuſe, beeing dead or benummed: and to accuſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13647:29"/> for well or ill doing: 3. In will, want of power, to will any true good, but to reſiſt it, and only to will that which is euill. 4. In affection, to hate good, and runne after ill. 5. In body, fitneſſe to begin ſinne, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing outward obiects and occaſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the ſenſes, and alſo to execute the ſame, when the heart hath conceiued it in word and deed: and this is called originall ſinne, which is in euery man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Doe all men continue in this ſinfull and curſed eſtate for euer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely the reprobate, whom God hath not decreed to ſaue, to manifeſt his iuſtice: for the elect, beeing predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to eternall life, are in this world in their appointed time called effectually, through Gods word and his ſpirit, iuſtified and ſanctified, and ſo ſhall continue in this eſtate of grace to bee glorified, for that God will alſo ſhew his mercy, and all for his owne glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are none of the reprobate euer in the eſtate of grace, and Gods fauour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No <hi>verily:</hi> though many of them, indued with the common gifts of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, may in outward appearance, for a time ſeeme to be of the elect, in the iudgement of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:13647:30"/>
                  <head>Q. Can any of the elect then be euer before God in the ſtate of damnation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No indeed: albeit both before their conuerſion: and alſo after they bee called, they falling by infirmity, and lying a time in their ſinne, may appeare in ſhew to the Church, to be none of the elect: yet can they not fall away, wholly or finally.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. May not men then liue as they liſt, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence he beeing a reprobate, cannot be ſaued, or an elect cannot be damned?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not ſo: for that one elect cannot but vſe the means which are ordained for him to walke, to make his election ſure to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which who ſo doth not, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What beleeue you concerning God the Sonne?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God the ſecond perſon in the Trinity, Chriſt Ieſus, the only natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Son begotten of the Father, our Lord, made man, conceiued &amp; ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt, ioyning two natures into one perſon, borne according to the promiſe, of the virgin Mary, who perfectly fulfilled the law, humbled &amp; ſuffered vnder Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, was crucified, bearing vpon him Gods curſe, and helliſh torments, who died and was buried, and being a while held captiue of death in the graue, hee was exalted, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13647:30"/> victoriouſly roſe againe the third day, and is aſcended vp into heauen, and there he ſits on the right hand of God his Father, hauing all power in heauen and earth to rule and gouerne his Church; where his manhood doth, and ſhall at all times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine (though in his godhead he be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with me euer) vntil he ſhal come from thence, to iudge vs all, here on earth, both quicke and dead at the laſt day; which day cannot be now farre of.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why ſhould he neede to be both God and man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he might be the only Mediatour betwixt God and man, to ſatisfie for ſinne, which neither the manhood by deſeruing, nor godhead by dying, alone could doe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why is he called Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To declare, that he was the promiſed Meſſias, and to ſignifie his offices, that he was annointed, not with material oyle, but with the gift of the ſpirit without meaſure, to be our King, Prieſt, and Prophet: from which name we are called Chriſtians, and are by him Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How is Chriſt a King?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I. He is King, not onely as God, but becauſe he is the head gouerning the Church, without any general Vicar vnder
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13647:31"/> him, by his word and ſpirit immediately, making lawes, and ordaining Miniſters to the gathering together and preſeruation thereof. II. By deſtroying Sathan, his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, vnbeleeuers, idolaters, heretikes, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the whole kingdome of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How is Chriſt a Prieſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I. By ſatisfying for all the ſinnes of the elect, by his paſſion and fulfilling of the law. II. For that he maketh prayer continually to God for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How is Chriſt a Prophet?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By immediatly reuealing from his father, his word and meanes of ſaluation contained in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why is he called Ieſus?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſignifie that he is a Sauiour to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true beleeuer: neither is there any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes of our ſelues, or by any other, either in part or whole, to obtaine ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but onely by him alone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why is he called Lord?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Becauſe we owe all homage and duty in loue to him, for our redemption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What beleeue you concerning the holy Ghoſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God, the third perſon in the Trinity, proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Father &amp;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13647:31"/> the Son, who ſpake by the Prophets, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the faithfull, ſanctifying them in part in this life, working by the word and holy motions, an vtter loathing of ſinne, and a heartie loue of righteouſneſſe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them into all truth, perſwading them of Gods fauour, teaching them in prayer, bearing them vp in temptation, quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, renewing, and increaſing his gifts in them; that they may know, beleeue, loue, and doe that which is good, which he will perfect fully in the life to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why did this God thus make, redeeme, ſanctifie, and hitherto preſerue you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I might praiſe his name, in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing godly, righteouſly, and ſoberly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all his commandements, in my calling, in all things, whatſoeuer my eſtate be, in this preſent world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doe you beleeue concerning the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That it is but one myſtical body whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther militant or triumphant, viſible or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or in earth, being a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Lords elect, holy by Chriſt, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, gathered of the diſperſed abroad, &amp; hauing ſpeciall prerogatiues aboue the reſt of mankind, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with Chriſt, &amp; one with another by the bond of the ſpirit,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13647:32"/> the forgiuenes of al ſins, the ioyful reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body, &amp; life euerlaſting, wherof I beleeue my ſelfe to be one, &amp; therefore, that the ſame things belong alſo vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the markes of the true Church here on earth?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Inwardly faith and loue, outwardly, (beſides the vncertaine notes, of vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, antiquity, and conſent) theſe two: Chriſts word truely preached, his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rightly adminiſtred, whereto adde, faithfull prayer, and holy diſcipline.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Is the Church of Rome a true Church of Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but of Antichriſt the Pope, the chiefe teacher of the doctrine of diuels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What reaſon haue you to diſallow that religion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For that it is a falſe religion. I. The author is the diuel. II. The meanes vſed to vphold it, are vnlawfull: 1. deceiued Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels: 2. vnwritten verities, and forged au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: 3. falſifying the Fathers: 4. corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Scripture, by adding thereto: 5. by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from it, by falſe interpreting: 6. retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the people in ignorance, by forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſtudy the word, &amp; teaching it in an vnknowne tongue: 7. pretending reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; ſhewing lying miracles: 8. counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13647:32"/> holines: 9. bloody perſecution. III. The matter of their religion is vntruths, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, hereſie, &amp; nouelties inuented by man. IV. The forme in the ſeruice ridiculous, by fooliſh geſtures: carnal, by fleſhly pomps and delights, their worſhip is by hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. V. The end to aduance men, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Saints, &amp; extolling mans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; merits. VI. The benefit gotten there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is nothing, becauſe it keepes a man in the ſtate of damnation: and alloweth the breach of all the 10. commandements. 1. To feare God by mens doctrines. 2. To worſhip images. 3. Magick &amp; coniuring. 4. idol-ſeruice. 5. Treaſon againſt Chriſtian Princes. 6. Aſſoyles for murtherers. 7. Stewes, and reſtraint of mariage. 8. Wages for no lawful labour, to Maſſe-mongers, &amp; for deceits. 9. To breake an oath to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian made lawfully. 10. That co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence is no ſinne. VII. Gods iudgments againſt many of the moſt fiery profeſſours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is neuer ſeene to happen to zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and conſtant profeſſours of the truth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What muſt bee done to maintaine the Church, and to ouerthrow hereſie, that deſtroies the foundation, errors corrupting religion, ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes breaking the peace of the Church, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtaining our profeſſion?</head>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:13647:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To cleaue only to the written word, which is both in time before, and in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aboue the Church, to iudge all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies in religion. 2. To call ſufficient men, and ordaine them miniſters to teach, allowing neceſſary maintenance; but ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no inſufficient to creep in, or to abide ſtill: neither the able to liue idlely, by care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, pride, or couetouſneſſe. 3. That there be a godly order eſtabliſhed &amp; peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably kept of euery one, without giuing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. 4. That there be a holy and right vſe continually of true diſcipline, to admoniſh, ſuſpend, and excommunicate obſtinate offenders whoſoeuer they be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are not the articles of your beleefe a prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but only a ſumme of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: which is one part of Gods word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the promiſes of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt, and is alſo a rule by which I muſt examine my faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What meane you by faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not faith to work miracles, which is paſt: nor hiſtoricall, only beleeuing that to be true which God ſaith; nor te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porary, to know, profeſſe, &amp; to teach Chriſt, feare to commit ſin, ſorrow after, to make ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to deſtroy the wicked, to make many
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13647:33"/> praiers wiſhing heauen, &amp; to liue for a time in ſhew honeſtly, yet out of Chriſt: but iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith is here meant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is iuſtifying faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a gracious and true perſwaſion in my heart, grounded vpon Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning Chriſt, whereby I do apply him and all his benefits to my ſelfe, beeing aſſured, that hee is my wiſedome, ſtrength, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and redemption, and that what hee hath done, it is as well done for mee, as for any other, and ſo is mine, as if my ſelfe had done it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How came you by this faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By the holy Ghoſt, working the ſame inwardly by the outward miniſtery of the Goſpell preached ordinarily, and is by the ſame word, ſacraments, and prayer, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, continued, and increaſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What profit reape you by this beleefe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I a wretched ſinner in my ſelf, being pardoned of ſinne, and Chriſt giuen to me; am in him the adopted ſonne of God, and righteous before him, my heart purged, my conſcience quieted, my imperfect workes doe pleaſe him, all croſſes are for comfort and further to ſaluation: holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels tend vpon me, heauen is mine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I am ſet at liberty from the curſe of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13647:34"/> the law, Satan, the world and fleſhly luſts, without feare of death, damnation, and hell fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Hath euery one this faith, and ſo theſe benefits?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely ſuch as ſhew repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the fruits of faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is repentance?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a true turning of my mind, will, and heart wholly from the world, the fleſh and diuell vnto God, with full purpoſe to attend carefully to the counſell of his word and ſpirit, and through the whole courſe of my life, readily and conſtantly endeauour to follow the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the true tokens of this true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. A continuall ſtriuing of the fleſh and ſpirit. 2. A hatred of my former va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, auoiding occaſion, company, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or example to ill, with loue vnfained to the contrary. 3. Increaſe of peace in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: with an affection for righteouſnes ſake. 4. A ioy full expecting and wiſhing Chriſts comming to iudgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. May not a man that truely repenteth, fall afterward?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes indeed, and into the ſame ſinne, or ſome other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:13647:34"/>
                  <head>Q. How then may a man be perſwaded, that his repentance was then true before?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. If this be of infirmity, feeling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and in the committing a diſlike ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for after true repentance ſinne is neuer wholly committed. 2. If that godly ſorrow follow, which is not either for earthly ſhame, temporall puniſhments, helliſh tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or loſſe of heauen: but for diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God ſo mercifull a Father, and this is called renewed repentance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How ſhould this appeare to be true?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. By an vtter loathing and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ſelfe for the ſinne newly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with deſire and perſwaſion of pardon. 2. A godly anger and burning zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſelfe, with taking reuenge, vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and practiſing ſtrictly the contrarie vertue for offending. 3. A watchfull care and continuall feare, leſt I fall afterwards at any time againe into the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What may comfort a troubled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Theſe things: 1. That God can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don any ſinne. 2. That he will by promiſe made, pardon euery penitent. 3. That he which feeleth a true deſire to leaue ſin, and to pleaſe God, is bound to beleeue his ſins are both pardonable &amp; pardoned. 4. That
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13647:35"/> doubting of ſaluation, with feare to offend God, is a ſigne of ſaluation. 5. No condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſuch as are in Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſins cannot damne them. 6. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification muſt not be iudged after ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, there is no perfection here, &amp; the beſt children of God haue grieuouſly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, &amp; haue felt this ſting of conſcience. 7. The aſſurance of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt not be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as men feele aſſurance in afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by the ſtability of Gods promiſes, from former comforts and tokens of grace, but in trouble from preſent deſires onely.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. You ſaid that your Godfathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers did promiſe for you, that you ſhold keep Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, tel me how many there be?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Ten, and are diuided into 2. Tables.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth the firſt Table teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The duty which I owe vnto God in holineſſe, whom I muſt loue with all my heart, with all my mind, and with all my ſoule, and with all my ſtrength, ſet downe in the foure firſt commandements, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the matter, manner, end, and time of Gods worſhip.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth the ſecond Table teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The duty which I owe vnto my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13647:35"/> which is euery one in righteouſneſſe, whom I muſt loue, as my ſelfe, ſet downe in the ſixe laſt Commandements, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his dignitie, life, body, goods, credit, and more ſpiritually all of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which be the Commaundements?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſame which God ſpake in the 20. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> ſaying, I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage, which is no commandement, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face vnto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the firſt commaundement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this commaundement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To make choice of one, and the true God, to be my God, and not to take that for God, which is not God by nature: the occaſion whereof was the luſting after ſtrange gods.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the things for bidden by this commaundement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Ignorance of God &amp; the truth, not to pray, diſtruſt of God, impatiency, to feare, loue, or ioy in the creature more then in the Creatour, to deny God, or his word, power, preſence, iuſtice or mercy, openly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13647:36"/> or ſecretly in heart: ſecurity without feare of God. The contrarie is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ſecond commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this commandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt neither worſhip falſe gods, nor this true God with ſelfe worſhip: but in ſpirit &amp; truth as his word onely teacheth. The occaſion of this commandement was a fooliſh deſire of a carnall worſhip, and a falſe conceipt, to be able to preſcribe a manner of worſhip to God of our ſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Idolatry, picturing of God, or Chriſt, Papiſtry, wil-worſhip, good intents with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrant, our owne fantaſies, mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, worſhip of images, pilgrimages: not to deſtroy errors, hereſies, and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of idolatry. The contrary is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the third commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not to bereaue God of his honour that is due vnto him: but in all things to giue him his due glory. The occaſion of this commandement was our readines to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13647:36"/> abuſe God, his name, word, and workes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To thinke or ſpeake of God, of his word, or works lightly or contemptuouſly, without reuerence: to ſweare by any thing, but by God: or by him without a calling, in our ordinary talke, where neither Gods glory, our brothers ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor magiſtrate requireth it: to ſweare falſely. So blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, witchcraft, coniuring, and curſing: to deny the known truth: to profeſſe piety, &amp; liue wickedly. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the fourth commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That euery day in the weeke I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare my ſelfe to keep the Lords day holy, that when it comes, it bee not prophaned, nor the publike worſhip of God letted, but furthered by me &amp; mine. The occaſion of this commandement, was our aptnes to fal from God, without daily meanes be vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To do vnneceſſary labours without godlineſſe and charity: Faires, iourneies, or vaine ſports, eating and drinking, that may hinder deuotion: not to heare Gods word preached, or to heare careleſly, ſleepily,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13647:37"/> with wearineſſe, or without purpoſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. To omit meditation and confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For Miniſters to omit ordinarily the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, to preach in a ſtraunge language vain-gloriouſly, falſely, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, flatteringly, or by conſtraint, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out chearefulnes; for any to abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues negligently or wilfully from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: the contrary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the fifth commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Honor thy father &amp; thy mother, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To preſerue the dignity of euery one by all meanes, that is any way to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, either by his place, age, or gifts, &amp; that no waies I diminiſh the ſame. The occaſion of this commandement was our proud &amp; enuious nature, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor to giue men their due.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Contempt of our betters, vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent behauiour towards them, by word or deede, to diſobey their lawfull commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, counſels, or aduice. All treaſon and rebellion: the contrary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ſixt commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt do no murther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt neither hurt nor hinder either
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13647:37"/> mine own life, or my neighbors life, but by al meanes preſerue the ſame. The occaſion of this commaundement, was our impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and vncharitable deſire of reuenge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Want of loue, anger, malice, enuy, grudging, a frowning countenance, deſire of reuenge: contention, railing, quarelling, mocking, offenſiue ieaſting, oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, murther, &amp; bodily hurt: to neglect to vſe means of health, or to hinder the ſame: to bee contentious, and not to ſeeke after peace. The contrary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ſeauenth commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt not any way hurt or impaire the chaſtity of my neighbour, but euery way ſeeke to preſerue the ſame. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this commandement, was our luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and fleſhly nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Luſtfull deſires, fornication, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with all occaſions hereunto: idleneſſe, wanton attire, a rolling eye, corrupt and vnhoneſt talke, wanton ſongs, laſciuious pictures, vnchaſte plaies, mixt dauncing of men and women, vnſeemely geſtures and acts, and companying with wantons.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13647:38"/> The contrary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the eight commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. doth this commandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I muſt not any way hinder or diminiſh my neighbours goods, but by all meanes preſerue &amp; increaſe the ſame. The occaſion hereof was our couetous nature, diſcontent euer with our preſent eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Pilfering and robbery, any way to take or keep that which is not ours vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: all theft, with al occaſions thereunto. Not to reſtore things found, borrowed, or left only to be kept in truſt: to giue what is not thine, either whole or part. Not to liue contentedly, all couetous deſires, idleneſſe out of calling, or litherneſſe in it. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ninth commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this commandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I muſt not diminiſh the good name or credit of my neighbour, whether friend or ſo, known or vnknown: but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerue the ſame. The occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this commandement was our ſeditious nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:13647:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Lying in ieaſt or earneſt, backbiting, ſlandering, reuealing ſecret infirmities and priuate offences before admonition, falſe witneſſe, by adding or detracting in words or ſenſe: to take a doubtfull matter in the worſt part: alſo all occaſions to this ſin, as enuie, diſdaine, anger, ſelfe-loue, to be too ſuſpitious, to be readie to receiue a falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port againſt our neighbour. The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the tenth commandement?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not couet, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doth this commandement teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I may not haue once an vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful luſt to that which is my neighbors: but for euer think good towards him. The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement was the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our' fleſh which intermitteth the work of the holy Ghoſt, by ſinful fantaſies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What things are hereby forbidden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Luſt, and ſudden motions againſt our neighbour, without conſent, which come from the corruption of nature: &amp; alſo ſuch as be offered by Sathan, or man, ſo farre as we giue any way conſent thereto: not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt il motions. The contrary is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are theſe commandements a prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but the ſumme of the morall law, which is the other part of Gods word, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13647:39"/> the righteouſnes of God, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me my ſins and curſed eſtate, and is a ſchoolemaſter vrging to Chriſt: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought in order firſt to be preached, and then the Goſpel ſhewing deliuerance, and giueth grace withall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How muſt this law be obeyed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Perfectly, willingly, and continually to God and my neighbour in thought, word, and deede, agreeing with Gods na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and our firſt eſtate by creation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Can you then keepe the commandements?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: for I breake them alwaies, either wittingly or ignorantly, in committing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, or omitting my duty: beſides that, I am guilty of them by naturall corruption, through <hi>Adams</hi> fall, before I could in my ſelfe, either thinke, ſpeake, or do any euill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is this breach of the law called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Sinne, whereby the infinite iuſtice of God is iniured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is then the reward of ſinne?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The infinite wrath of God, and his vengeance for euer, in this world and in the world to come, is due for the leaſt ſinne, whether it be mortall or veniall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſin in this life?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> In name, ſlander and ſhame: in goods, loſſes: in his bodie, paines and ſickneſſe: all
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13647:39"/> maner of aduerſity, &amp; all corporal plagues befalling in this life. In the ſoule, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, madneſſe, an ill conſcience accuſing, benummed, dead, or deſperate: a heauie ſtony heart, likewiſe diſobedient and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked children, a diſloyall wife, falſe friends, cruell aduerſaries: to be ſuffered to fall into ſinne, God taking away his grace, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſin of whoredome, as a puniſhment for ſinne. And laſtly, bodily death, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or ſudden.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Comes alwaies afflictions as puniſhments for ſinne?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Afflictions firſt came for ſinne, but are alſo to try our patience, faith, and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: to weane vs from our ſelues and the world, &amp; to become co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable to Chriſt in perſecutions: that Gods power and goodnes may appeare to vs: &amp; theſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be called fatherly chaſtiſements of the godly to euery one in his meaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How may you perſwade your ſelfe, that afflictions are chaſtiſements, and not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Iudge, when they befall?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> If I can make good vſe of them, to further me in godlineſſe: els are they but fore-runners of my eternall deſtruction, as they be to the reprobate, that are not bettered by them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:13647:40"/>
                  <head>Q. What are the puniſhments for ſinne after death?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſeparation from God, the loſſe of heauen, and of the ioyfull company of Angels, Patriarkes, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, &amp; Saints, the true profeſſours of Chriſt, for euer: to be damned with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, &amp; his angels, the infernall fiends, with all the wicked accurſed to hell, there to be tormented vnſpeakably without end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How muſt you eſcape this vengeance of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By no good deeds that I can doe, but only faith in Ieſus Chriſt, who is the merit onely and wholly of my ſaluation: &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whome my beſt thoughts, words, and deedes, are abhominable before God, ſeeme they neuer ſo holy in mine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens iudgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why then ſhould you doe good workes, if you cannot nor may not thinke to win heauen by them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt do good works, becauſe I am already ordained to be ſaued. 1. To make my electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the more ſure to my ſelf, which is certaine with God. 2. To ſhew my loue and thankfulnes to God for it, by obeying his commandements. 3. To confirme the conuerted, and to winne others not yet
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13647:40"/> called. 4. To ſtop the mouthes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; to ſhame them by well doing, when they ſpeake ill of v 8. 5. To benefit one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our quiet peaceablenes in Church and common-wealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are not then workes neceſſary?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes verily, to ſuch as will haue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation: for without works, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, hearing the word, knowledge, faith, loue, hope, faſting, ſorrow, prayer, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, are in vaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is a good worke?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Whatſoeuer is done or ſpoken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting, from the warrant of Gods word, of a true beleeuer, in charity, and to Gods glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Though our good workes merit not, may we not yet thinke that they ſhall be rewarded?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes verily: for in his mercy he hath ſo promiſed to doe, both in this world, and in the world to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the bleſſing and reward in this life?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Increaſe of knowledge in Gods word: aſſurance that his gifts in vs are graces, and not only common fauours: al earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, a good name, wealth, honor, friends, and proſperous ſucceſſe, ſo farre as it ſhall be for Gods glory, and my ſpirituall ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:13647:41"/>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>faith, to apprehend as much as ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. 6. My hope to waite without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing God either time, place, manner, or quantity of the matter. 7. My will, to vſe afterwards all the honeſt meanes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to obtaine the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What be the true properties of prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. That it be in true loue: for we muſt remember to pray for all our brethren not departed this life, for there is no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. 2. It muſt be made only to God, for him only can we call heauenly Father, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Saints nor Angels. 3. In the name of Chriſt, through whom onely hee is our Father by adoption. 4. In faith, for that hee is a Father, and will not deny his children. 5. Without a carnall conceipt of God, vaine babling, or wandering thoughts: for he is in heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which be the ſixe petitions?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Hallowed be thy name, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What doe theſe teach you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſum of al the things which I can lawfully aske at Gods hands, for body or ſoule: wherof the firſt 3. concerne the glory of God, and the latter 3. the good of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the firſt petition, and what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The firſt is, <hi>Hallowed bee thy name:</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:13647:41"/> and I deſire therein, in the firſt place, that I and all other may acknowledge God ſo truly, in his word and workes, as in euery of our thoughts, words, and deeds, he may be highly worſhipped and praiſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the ſecond, and what deſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſecond is, <hi>Thy kingdome come:</hi> and I deſire that he will ſend vs the meanes, thus to honour his name, that is, his word and Spirit, with all things that do further thereunto: that ſo the elect may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and Chriſt come to the laſt iudgement to giue vs his kingdome of glorie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the third petition, and what deſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The third is, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that as we pray to do, not ours, but his will, as all his commandements and word teacheth vs: and as the bleſſed Saints and Angels doe in heauen, heartily without hypocriſie, willingly, without grudging, readily without lingring, faithfully without ſiniſter reſpects, ioyfully without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and conſtantly without wauering, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the fourth petition, and what deſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The fourth is, <hi>Giue vs this, &amp;c.</hi> and I
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13647:42"/> deſire, that he will prouide thoſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for our bodies, without which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerue him: and that we may depend patiently vpon his prouidence, vſing dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent labour, and all honeſt meanes to help our ſelues and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the fifth petition, and what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The fifth is, <hi>And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, &amp;c.</hi> and I deſire that he would forgiue al of vs, friend or foe, our ſinnes, leſt they either hinder vs of the former mercies, or cauſe them to be taken from vs: and that he will perſwade our conſciences, that we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, by giuing vs grace to forgiue freely, and to forget thoſe offences, whereby in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, or any way, our neighbours haue beene grieuous vnto vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the ſixth and laſt petition, and what deſire you in it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſixth is, <hi>Leade vs not into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> and I deſire, that as he will pardon vs, ſo he would alſo giue vs the gift of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, that though we be tempted, yet may we ouercome, and be deliuered from ſinne and Satan, and neuer fall againe any more from God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the confirmation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For thine is the kingdome, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:13647:42"/>
                  <head>Q. What learne you by this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I do learn hereby 2. things: 1. that it is a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to moue God, but to ſtir vp our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. &amp; to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our faith in asking.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How doth it this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> When it teacheth mee to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the kingdome of God our Father, that is, his dominion and right ouer al: and that his power is the greateſt to compell all to doe what he will, and as he will: and his glory the higheſt, which himſelfe maintaines, and we ſeeke aboue all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the ſecond thing we learne?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 2. A thankſgiuing &amp; praiſing of God, which we ought to vſe in the end, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of praier: which is done, in giuing to God his owne, the rule, power, &amp; glorie, which we deſire him to manifeſt by gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; we wil acknowledg the ſame; not for a time, but for euer &amp; euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Which is the concluſion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> This word, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What meane you by this word?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I am perſwaded by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reaſons, that my requeſt is granted, and ſhall be performed, as my Father ſhall ſee it conuenient for me and his glorie, in time and place. And therefore I ſay, <hi>it is ſo,</hi> or <hi>it ſhall be,</hi> which is <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13647:43"/>
               <head>The fifth part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is a Sacrament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a viſible ſigne, and ſeale of inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible graces, commanded &amp; ordained with a promiſe by Chriſt in the Church, to be adminiſtred publikely, by a lawfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, with the preaching of the word: which Sacrament with all the rites thereof doth repreſent and conuay by proportion and relation, in the preſent vſe, inuiſible graces, firſt Chriſt, and then all his benefits, for further aſſurance of the ſame things, which God hath made by the promiſe of his word, vnto a true beleeuer, who is with Chriſt by the H. Ghoſt vnited &amp; made on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What meane you by Chriſt, and all his benefits?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Whole Chriſt, God &amp; man, with his righteouſnes, iuſtice, holines, &amp; redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who as he is Chriſt, one perſon of two natures, is truly ſaid to be really preſent in the Sacrament, not properly in his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but by the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of properties.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How may you be ſure that you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued true benefite by the Sacraments?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> If I do feele a dying to ſinne, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto righteouſnes, getting ſtrength, and alſo increaſing therein daily, by the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13647:43"/> force of Chriſts death and reſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How many Sacraments are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Two, and no more: Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is Baptiſme?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is the firſt Sacrament in the new Teſtament, by which ſuch as are within the couenant, are either waſhed, ſprinkled, or dipped in the water, in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the outward ſigne and rite?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Water and waſhing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the inuiſible grace?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The blood of Chriſt which clenſeth vs of all ſin, original &amp; actual, paſt &amp; to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Are we then no ſinners?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes in our ſelues: for originall ſinne ſtill is ſinne in vs, but wee are waſhed from it, becauſe it ſhall not be imputed, nor any ſinne elſe vnto me a true beleeuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Who are to be baptized?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not only ſuch as be of yeares, that can and do teſtifie their faith: but alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of either father or mother profeſſing Chriſt &amp; baptized: for the promiſe of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation belongs to them &amp; to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Is baptiſme ſo neceſſary to ſaluation, that without it children cannot be ſaued?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is neceſſary to al that haue it, but not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13647:44"/> of neceſſity, to ſuch as cannot rightly come by it: for not the want, but the careles neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and contempt thereof condemneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How oft ſhould we be baptized?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> But once, for wee may not be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed againe after true baptiſme: for beeing once borne, wee cannot bee borne againe naturally, nor ſpiritually.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What is the Lords Supper?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is the latter Sacrament in the new Teſtament, whereby we are nouriſhed and preſerued in the Church to eternall life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What be the outward ſignes?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Bread and wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What be the things ſignified?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the rites?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Miniſter &amp; receiuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the actions of the Miniſter?</head>
                  <p>A. 1. To take the bread and wine into his hands. 2. to bleſſe it. 3. to breake the bread, and powre forth the wine. 4. to offer and giue them to the receiuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the actions of the receiuer?</head>
                  <p>A. 1. To take the bread &amp; wine offered into his hand: 2. to eate the one, and drink the other, and ſo digeſt &amp; concoct them, as that they feele nouriſhment to the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What learne you by all theſe actions?</head>
                  <p>A. I am aſſured that the viſible actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13647:44"/> the Miniſter do repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſpiritual acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God the Father to my ſoule, who hath decreed his Son, and elected him the Mediator, to haue his body broken, &amp; his precious blood ſhed for me, being offered to all, but giuen only to the true beleeuer, that can by the hand of faith take hold of him, who ſhewes as liuely the vertue of his death to preſerue his ſoule, as the vertue of the bread &amp; wine is felt to noriſh the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Is the bread turned into Chriſts bodie, and is the wine into his very blood?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No verily: for then, 1. it were no Sacrament, 2. it is againſt reaſon, 3. againſt ſcripture, 4. againſt an article of our Creed, 5. againſt the iudgment of ancient Fathers true writings, 6. againſt the iudgement of reformed chriſtian churches, 7. againſt the opinion of holy Martyrs, who ſhed their blood for the contrary, 8. it is againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of our ſenſes, that the bread ſhold be fleſh, or wine blood: neither is Chriſts body in, with, or about the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Is there then no difference of this bread and wine, from that which we vſe commonly?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> There is no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the ſubſtance, but in the holy vſe: being at that time ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to be ſignes of Chriſts body &amp; blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. May euery one offer to receiue that will?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely ſuch as come prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13647:45"/> and be fit, that both are able in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to examine, and alſo by a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wil iudge themſelues, whether they be in any meaſure prepared thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What if you come vnprepared?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am an vnworthy receiuer, prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods wrath againſt mee, and ſo eate and drinke my owne damnation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Who are thoſe that ought not to come?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Open impenitent ſinners, fooles, mad perſons, children, all that be of yeares, and yet ignorant, not being able to try &amp; iudge themſelues: &amp; if ſuch prophane ones do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they are not to be admitted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What be thoſe things whereof you muſt trie and iudge your ſelfe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. Of my knowledge, concerning my miſerable eſtate through ſin; of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; our deliuerance by Chriſt, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this Sacrament. 2. Of my beleefe in Chriſt, which I may doe by the Creed. 3. Of my repentance towards God, for old and new ſins, examined by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. 4. Of my brotherly loue, which I do owe to euery one, which I may try and iudge by my forgiuing others, as I deſire God to forgiue mee, and by my ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſatisfie whome I haue offended of my knowledge either in word or deede.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. May any by omitting theſe duties be free
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13647:45"/> from ſinne, if therefore they will not receiue the Sacrament with others?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: for as to come vnprepared is damnation, ſo to neglect to prepare for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny earthly occaſion, is a great wickednes, ſuch liuing in diſobedience without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and charitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Why doe you goe to the Lords Supper?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To teſtifie my loue in obedience to God commanding. 2. To ſtrengthen my faith being weake. 3. To maintaine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the holy communion &amp; fellowſhip of brotherly loue amongſt vs the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt: &amp; 4. to keepe a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his death till his ſecond comming.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. How muſt you be exerciſed in the time of adminiſtration, and afterwards?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt 1. meditate vpon the death &amp; paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, how grieuouſly I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. 2. Gods endles mercy. 3. the vnity and fellowſhip that is amongſt the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church with Chriſt, and one with another: reioycing in heart, and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God therfore with the congregation. Afterwards 1. I muſt giue almes to the needy brethren, &amp; doe other good workes of charitie in token of thankfulneſſe, that day eſpecially, for ſo great a mercy. 2. Grow from thenceforth in obedience, faith, and vnfained loue to my liues end.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:13647:46"/>
               <head>The ſixth part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. Can you briefly ſhew me any rules to be obſerued, that you may doe ſo, as you haue bin taught?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I. Euery morning before other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I muſt, 1. thanke God for my ſafety, 2. deſire pardon of ſin, 3. Gods further prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt ghoſtly and bodily enemies.</p>
                  <p>II. I muſt know that, that day, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times after giuen me to liue in, are for more earneſt repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, encreaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, and practiſe of godlineſſe: and therefore of theſe continually I muſt be mindfull, ſetting ſome part of the day aſide for reading, hearing, or meditating vpon heauenly things: that the vanities of the world ſhort &amp; vncerten cary me not away.</p>
                  <p>III. I muſt haue, or els prepare my ſelf to ſome particular calling, fit to keepe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idlenes, and to exerciſe the duties of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which calling muſt I be both ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, &amp; profitable to others: to which, 1. I muſt betake me ſpeedily, that no time be loſt: 2. to do therin as I would be done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: 3. to ſeeke firſt in my labour Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my own good with my neighbours profit: 4. labour therin painfully &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in aduerſity vſing good meanes, hoping for proſperitie, in proſperity neglecting no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13647:46"/> humble duties for feare of aduerſity: 5. my preſent eſtate I muſt accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it euer the beſt for me, and moſt for Gods glory: 6. I muſt not feare to ſpend where God &amp; charitie requireth, ſparing from idle expences, and onely lay vp, for the time to come, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhal remaine, when I haue diſcharged neceſſary duties honeſtly and righteouſly.</p>
                  <p>IV. I muſt retire my ſelfe ſometime fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my weariſome labour, when I ſee need, which muſt be: 1. at times conuenient: 2. in things lawfull: 3. ſhort, delightſome to the mind, &amp; healthful for the body: 4. to make me more chearefull to returne to labour, and not to draw me to loiter and to idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, no end appointed to man or beaſt.</p>
                  <p>V. I muſt warily ſee to mine own waies. I. My thoughts &amp; heart muſt: 1. be far from vnlawfull affection: 2. vpon lawfull things on earth moderate, &amp; no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> needs: 3. vpon God &amp; heauenly things often, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently, &amp; reuerently: 4. that I ſtriue againſt ſelfe-loue, thinking of my ſelfe baſely, and waxe, by more and greater gifts, the more humble &amp; leſſe enuious: 5. Of other I muſt thinke highly and charitably, iudging well without ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, what I heare or ſee good in them, receiuing with ioy: and hoping of better what I ſee or heare to be ill in them, taking doubtfull words or deeds from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:13647:47"/> in the better part. II. My eies muſt be ſhut againſt obiects to ſin, that they let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not into my heart, to ſtirre vp ill motions: but quick to obſerue euery good example and occaſion to goodnes. III. My eare muſt be exerciſed in hearing the truth, good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, friendly admonitions, and godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, but ſhut againſt flattery, lyings, ſlander, filthy &amp; wicked ſpeeches. IV. My tongue muſt keepe ſilent, vnleſſe iuſt cauſe &amp; conuenient time &amp; place be to ſpeake. In ſpeaking the matter muſt 1. be gracious to profit the hearers, and alſo neceſſary to be vttered: 2. in wiſedome regarding cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: 3. in ſinceritie to ſpeak it from the heart: 4. ſpeaking of God &amp; his word, it muſt be religiouſly and ioyfully: of our ſelues modeſtly, of others louingly: 5. to praiſe moderatly without contempt: to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe meekely ſhewing loue, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by neceſſity rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of will, to ſpeak of other mens faults, expreſſing ſorrow in vttering: 6. to ſpeake well of men in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, what good we know of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, &amp; in preſence without flattery: 7. to vſe few words and effectuall to the matter without tediouſnes: 8. not to talke of needleſſe matters, or which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes vs not, as buſi-bodies, neither of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13647:47"/> any thing againſt religion, charity, commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good, or chaſtity. V. My behauiour, 1. it muſt be lowly to ſuperiours, 2. gentle to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, and 3. louely to familiars. VI. My apparell, it muſt bee firſt for neceſſity, and then for honeſt decency, as wee are able, &amp; agreeing with our calling. VII. My diet muſt be 1. ſparing, ordinarily a kinde of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting rather then a feaſting: 2. taking my food with hunger &amp; thirſting: 3. at ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houres: 4. that thereby 1. my ſtrength may be maintained &amp; encreaſed, 2. my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and deuotion nothing hindred, 5. that we be prepared in the beginning, may feele a neceſſity &amp; pray to God: and in the end ſufficient refreſhing, may thank God.</p>
                  <p>VI. I muſt take heed what company I keepe with, 1. that I make my familiars none but honeſt and religious, 2. that they be my equals in eſtate and place, not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours to auoid ſuſpicion of pride; nor too much inferiours, leſt it bring contempt, 3. that of theſe, not many, but one of all, I wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, deliberately, &amp; with much triall, chuſe my ſecret friend, 4. that in going or kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with any, I muſt euer purpoſe either to do good, or receiue ſome.</p>
                  <p>VII. At night, the time of reſt, 1. I muſt call to mind Gods benefits receiued, either
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13647:48"/> by preuenting euill, or by bringing good vpon me, to thanke him. 2. I muſt recount what I haue done, either in euill to repent, or what good I performed, to iudge either of my encreaſing or decaying in grace: ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing more for the duties omitted &amp; ſins committed, then ioyful of any good done. 3. In taking reſt I muſt commit my ſelfe to God, by a deuout &amp; faithful praier, as thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no more to riſe. 4. to haue my laſt thoughts of heauenly things, by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or recalling ſomewhat to minde, of which I haue either heard, or learned out of Gods word. 5. that I take ſleep to refreſh nature, and not to ſatisfie ſlouthfull fleſh.</p>
                  <p>VIII. and laſt is, that all the weeke long I remember to labour in my calling, and diſpoſe of my ordinary buſines, that I bee prepared for the Lords day to keep it ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but eſpecially at the end of the weeke, ſo that when it comes, I may neither by them breake it, or be hindered. Thus liuing to God holily, to my neighbour charitably, &amp; towards my ſelfe ſoberly, my conſcience ſhall bee comforted, my weake brethren ſtrengthened, the ſtrong confirmed, the wicked made aſhamed, the diuell confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and God greatly Glorified.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13647:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
